FAMILY PLANNING ADVOCATES OF NEW YORK STATE RECORDS (APAP044) 1976-2004
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives
Family Planning Advocates of New York State Records1976-2004
nam_apap044
Family Planning Advocates of New York State
7.72
Family Planning Advocates of New York State was established in the 1970's by the affiliates of Planned Parenthood of New York State in an effort to expand the capacity of its organization to affect public policy through lobbying and education.
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, University at Albany, SUNY
Administrative History
Family Planning Advocates of New York State was established in the 1970s by the affiliates of Planned Parenthood of New York State in an effort to expand the capacity of its organization to affect public policy through lobbying and education. Planned Parenthood affiliates had previously been involved in an organization of family planning activists, the New York State Coalition for Family Planning, organized in 1972. This coalition worked with the administrative branch of state government, but was financially unable to lobby the legislature. In January 1976, the Planned Parenthood affiliates, in conjunction with the New York State Coalition for Family Planning, opened a Family Planning Public Affairs Office. The purpose of this office was to educate lawmakers and the community to the needs and services of family planning providers in New York State; act as a resource to the legislature; and gather and disseminate information to family planning providers and public policy makers.
In November of 1976 it was decided that in order to make the impact that was thought possible, a greater infusion of money and a stronger commitment to staff would have to be made to the Family Planning Office by its supporters. At the same time it was becoming clear that the Coalition for Family Planning was not able to continue operating with its existing sources of funding. A Transition Committee, comprised of members from Planned Parenthood affiliates and the Board of the Coalition, was appointed in January 1977 to develop a plan to incorporate the functions of the Coalition and the Family Planning Office. The stated purpose of the organization was to represent to the New York State government the views of Planned Parenthood affiliates, other related organizations, and family planning consumers. This would be done by: developing a statewide family planning public policy program; providing statewide public policy leadership; informing members of the legislature and agencies of state government about family planning objectives as related to public policy; informing family planning agencies, other interested groups, organizations, and individuals concerning state legislative proposals and actions; educating the public regarding responsible reproductive activity; and by coordinating litigation when indicated.
On April 19, 1977, delegates from Planned Parenthood Affiliates, other organizations and individuals met. They agreed to incorporate Family Planning Advocates of New York State as a 501 (c) (4) organization. A slate of officers was elected; members of the Executive Committee were appointed; and by-laws were drafted. A full-time Executive Director, Shirley Gordon, was appointed. A more secure funding base was established with the Planned Parenthood Affiliates committing themselves to assuming the major cost of operation.
The by-laws of Family Planning Advocates designate all affiliates of Planned Parenthood Federation of America, Inc. as sustaining members, and designate all other organizations and individuals supporting progressive family planning as non-sustaining members. The by-laws also define the members of the board of directors by duties and powers. The Planned Parenthood affiliates are each represented by one Board member, the sponsoring organization members are as a group represented by 5 board members, and the individual members are as a group represented by 5 board members. The board meets in the fall of each year to elect officers, approve the annual budget of the corporation, and to delegate the duties and authority to individual officers and committees. Directors of the board do not receive any stated compensation but may receive reimbursement for expenses in attending the annual meeting.
Officers of Family Planning Advocates consist of a president, two vice-presidents, a secretary, a treasurer, "and such additional officers as the Board of Directors may from time to time elect". From the slates provided by the Nominating Committee, the officers are elected at the annual board meeting for a one year term. The president functions as chief executive officer.
There are four major committees of Family Planning Advocates of New York State. The Executive Committee is composed of the Officers of the Corporation and six additional members, which meets "not less frequently than once every 2 months". Standing Committees consist of three or more members appointed by the Board of Directors with a chair appointed by the president. The Budget and Finance Committee is chaired by the Treasurer and members are selected by the Treasurer. The Nominating Committee, comprised of 5 members, "at least 3 of whom shall be former members or members of the Board of Directors", prepare slates of nominees for the Board of Directors, the officers, the Executive Committee, and the Nominating Committee.
Scope and Content Information
The records of Family Planning Advocates of New York State include administrative history, by-laws, meeting minutes, personnel policies, correspondence (including press releases), newsletters, issues files, publications, and reports documenting the inner workings and the issues addressed by the organization.
The largest section of the records is the Correspondence series. This series traces the political realm that Family Planning Advocates worked within and has influence over. Most of the correspondence also includes attached material such as research papers, positional statements, survey results and interpretations, news clippings, and copies of published articles relating to the organization and its interests.
Arrangement of the Collection
Collection is divided into 5 topic series.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Shirley Gordon, Director of the Family Planning Advocates of New York State in March 1990, by Family Planning Advocates in August 2004, and by Family Planning Advocates in August 2006.
Related collections in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives include the records of the National Organization for Women-New York State (APAP-029) as well as other collections in the subject guide for Women.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Subject and Genre Headings
Family Planning Advocates of New York State.; Planned Parenthood Federation of America.; Birth control -- New York (State).; Abortion services -- Law and legislation -- New York (State).; Lobbying -- New York (State).; Women’s rights -- New York (State).; Medical care; Minutes.; Newsletters.; Medicine and Health Care; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Women
Container List
- Administrative Records, Undated; 1; 1.3
  The text Action Impact: A Manual For Family Planning Advocates published in 1988 by the organization details the manner in which family planning field operators could make legislative and organizational recommendations. The origins of the organization are outlined with a brief history called "Family Planning Advocates of New York State, Inc...How It All Began". The policy folders trace the issues of contraception, teenage pregnancy, parental consent for abortion, infant mortality rates, preventative care, and sex education. These issues were reported by the media and researched by local and federal government departments. The issues contained in the files ultimately were adopted as Family Planning Advocates' policies as recommendations to reproductive organizations and to legislators for state and federal guidelines and laws. Information on legislative activity is found in update sheets and as agenda brochures outlining the schedule and speakers used at issues conferences. This material document how the state legislature was enacting laws and debating issues in conference that would impact the organization's monies and policies. The personnel policies dating from 1979 appear to be the typewritten original document of "Personnel Policies and Practices for Salaried Employees", outlining the employment practices of the organization as it affected the staff. Also in the Administrative series are the minutes of meetings. The minutes are not of the general membership, but of the Executive Committee mostly, interspersed with the minutes of the annual Board meeting. Any documents that were used for focus in the meetings by either the Executive Committee or the Board of Directors are included and affixed to the minutes of the meeting when they were used. There are two alphabetical arrangements of the records in this series - those transferred in 1990 and those transferred in 2004 and 2006. Administrative records including Board and Executive Committee meeting minutes and other materials, particularly from the late 1980s-2000, can be found in the Correspondence series as those documents were mailed to the relevant constituencies.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Action Impact: A Manual For Family Planning Advocates, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - By-laws, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Family Planning Services, 1976; Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Family Planning Advocates Policies, 1977-1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - History of Family Planning Advocates of New York State, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Legislative Conference Agendas, 1987-1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Personnel Policies, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Policy Statements, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Proposal for Albany, New York Office of Family Planning Advocates, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Summary of Laws and Regulations, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Amelia Case, 1994-1996 (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
  - Annual Meeting, Board Reports, Slides, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Board Manual, 25th Anniversary Committee, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Board Manual, 1999-2000 (Box 9, Folder 6-8)
  - Legislative Conference Programs, 1990-2000 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Legislative Update, 1990-1997 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1995-2000 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Memos, 1996-1997 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - New Voices, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - New Voices, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 14-15)
  - New Voices, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 16-18)
  - New Voices, Mission Statement, Undated (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - New Voices, Returned Surveys, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - New Voices, Wheel Of Life Instructions, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 21)
- Correspondence, Undated; 2; 5.18
  Correspondence was sent from Family Planning Advocates of New York State to various organizations and individuals: affiliates and field operators, the Governor of New York State, legislators, and editors of newspapers. Also included is correspondence between the Board of Directors and the Executive Committee, general letters to the membership, letters to presidents of other Family Planning Advocates organizations, letters to physicians connected to public health services organizations, members of the clergy, and press releases. All correspondence is typed and on letterhead and is representative of the communication sent by Family Planning Advocates of New York State to others; little of the correspondence represents what the organization received. Administrative records including Board and Executive Committee meeting minutes and other materials, particularly from the late 1980s-2000, are also interfiled with correspondence as those documents were mailed to the relevant constituencies.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1984 January-1984 June (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1984 July-1984 December (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1985 January-1985 June (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 1985 July-1985 December (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, 1986 January-1986 May (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, 1986 June-1986 December (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1987 January-1987 May (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 1987 June-1987 September (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 1987 October-1987 December (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, 1988 January-1988 March (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1988 April-1988 August (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1988 September-1988 October (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1988 November-1988 December (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1990 January-1990 March (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1990 April-1990 June (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1990 July-1990 September (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1990 October-1990 December (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1991 January-1991 March (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1990 April-1990 June (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1991 July-1991 September (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1991 October-1991 December (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1992 January-1992 March (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1992 April-1992 June (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1992 July-1992 September (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1992 October-1992 November (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1992 December (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1993 January-1993 March (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1993 April-1993 May (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1993 June-1993 August (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1993 September-1993 October (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1993 November-1993 December (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1994 January-1994 February (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1994 March-1994 April (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1994 May-1994 June (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1994 July-1994 August (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1994 September-1994 October (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1994 November-1994 December (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1995 January-1995 February (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1995 March (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1995 April (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1995 May (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1995 June (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1995 July (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1995 August (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1995 September (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1995 October (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1995 November-1995 December (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1996 January-1996 February (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1996 March-1996 April (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1996 May (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1996 June-1996 July (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1996 August-1996 September (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1996 October (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1996 November (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1996 December (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1996 March-1996 June (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1996 September-1996 December (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1997 January-1997 February (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1997 March (Box 7, Folder 4-5)
  - Correspondence, 1997 April (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
  - Correspondence, 1997 June (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1997 July (Box 7, Folder 9-10)
  - Correspondence, 1997 August-1997 September (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1997 October (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1997 November-1997 December (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1998 January-1998 February (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1998 March (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1998 April (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1998 May (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1998 October-1998 November (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1999 January-1999 July (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1999 August-1999 December (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Albany Memo, Undated; 3; 0.32
  The Albany Memo is the newsletter published monthly by Family Planning Advocates of New York State. These one to two-page newsletters contain information on the organization's activities and the laws being enacted related to family planning. Also included is information on reproductive issues and the organization's role in fostering responsible family planning. Published in the newsletter are the voting records of state legislators for issues that deal directly with birth control, abortion, parental consent, Medicaid funding for abortion, pre-natal care, and related issues Often whole bills before the state legislature are found printed in the Albany Memo.
  - Albany Memo, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Albany Memo, 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Albany Memo, 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Albany Memo, 1985-1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Albany Memo, 1990-2000 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Subject Files, Undated; 4; 0.42
  This series documents issues such as New York State's system for preventive care; preventing unwanted pregnancy; cartoons on reproductive health; syphilis, gonorrhea, chlamydia, and other sexually transmitted diseases; sterilization; teenage pregnancy; a news clipping on infant mortality rates; sex education; parental consent; abortion; and family planning services.
  - Abortion, 1978; Undated; 1990 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Adolescents, 1987; 1989 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Infant Death Rate Wall Street Journal, 1985 July 23 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - New York's Key System for Preventative Care, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Parental Consent, 1981-1990 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Preventing Unintended Pregnancy, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Reproductive Health Cartoons, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Sex Education, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Sterilization, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Syphilis, Sexually Transmitted Diseases, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Teenage Pregnancy, 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - American Cartoonist Comment on Reproductive Health Issues, 1987-2000 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Religious Health Restrictions, 2004 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Sex Ed Wheel Of Fortune, Undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Publications and Reports, Undated; 5; 0.5
  The publications and reports are devoted to the many aspects of reproductive health and choice and the costs incurred, as well as some issues before the legislature.
  - The Impact of the Hyde Amendment on Medically Necessary Abortions, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Task Force on Medicaid Rates for Family Planning Services: Establishment of a System for Financing Treatment or Diagnostic Center Services, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Teenage Pregnancy, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Benefits and Costs of the Family Planning Program, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Long Term Trends in Public Assistance Recipients: Aid to Families with Dependent Children, New York City, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Costs and Benefits of Title XX: Family Planning Services in Texas, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Benefits and Costs of Family Planning-An Update Report, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Making Choices: Evaluating the Health Risks and Benefits of Birth Control Methods, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Adolescent Pregnancy, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Family Planning as a Cost Containment Initiative: Report of the Director's Special Task Force, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Governor's Task Force on Adolescent Pregnancy, I, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Governor's Task Force on Adolescent Pregnancy, II, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Report of Public Child Fatality Review Committee, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Black Health Issues, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Governor's Task Force on Adolescent Pregnancy, III, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - The U.S. International Family Planning Program: Under Siege, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Healthy Children: Investing in the Future, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Women at Risk: The Need for Family Planning Services, State and County Estimates, 1987 (1988) (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - When the Conventional Wisdom is Wrong: A Reexamination of the Role of Abortion As an Issue in Federal Elections, 1974-86, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - New York's Children in 1989: Society at Risk, A Report of New York State Project 2000 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Reproductive Health Initiative for FY 1990-91: A Proposal to Promote Early Intervention for Adolescents and Low Income Women, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Teenage Pregnancy and Too-Early Childbearing: Public Costs, Personal Consequences, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - The Facts Speak Louder: Planned Parenthood's Critique of 'The Silent Scream', Undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Fact Sheets, ca. 1995-2000 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Reproductive Health Laws and Regulations, 2000 (Box 12, Folder 2)